{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This lake is named for a tribe whose members called themselves “the long tails.” The Fenians crossed this body of water and feigned raids near its eastern end at the Welland Canal. This lake was the site of a battle in the War of 1812 during which Oliver Hazard Perry noted, “We have met the enemy and they are ours” and led to the Americans securing Detroit. For 10 points, what Great Lake shares its name with a canal running from Buffalo to Albany?",
      "answer": "Lake Erie"
    },
    {
      "question": "This king signed the Treaty of Aberconwy with Llywelyn the Last. Alongside Gilbert de Clare, this king commanded his father's forces at the Battle of Evesham [eve-shum], where he defeated Simon de Montfort to end the Second Barons' War. This king, who undertook a successful conquest of Wales, crushed the upstart William Wallace at the Battle of Falkirk. For 10 points, name this English king who succeeded Henry III and was known as \"The Hammer of the Scots\" and “Longshanks”.",
      "answer": "Edward I"
    },
    {
      "question": "An artist from this country was arrested after depicting this country's revolution in the painting The March of Humanity. Several skeletons in graduation caps appear in \"Gods of the Modern World,\" a work one artist from this country painted at Dartmouth College. A purported depiction of Lenin in a painting by an artist from this country led Nelson Rockefeller to destroy it against its artist's wishes. For 10 points, name this native country of the painter of Man at the Crossroads, Diego Rivera.",
      "answer": "Mexico"
    },
    {
      "question": "It's not the UK, but a team from this country sponsored by Emirates lost eight straight races to lose the 2013 America’s Cup. This country contests both the Bledisloe Cup and the Freedom Cup in a sport where they are represented by a team that uses a silver fern as an emblem and performs the Kapa o Pango and the Ka Mate. For 10 points, name this country whose rugby union team, the All Blacks, performs the haka, a ceremonial war dance of its indigenous Maori people.",
      "answer": "New Zealand"
    },
    {
      "question": "For her role during this period, Marina Mniszech entered folklore as Marinka the Witch. Kuzma Minin and Dmitry Pozharsky became patriotic heroes for defeating a Polish army during this period after raising funds from the city of Nizhny Novgorod. No fewer than three men were killed after falsely claiming to be the deceased Tsarevich Dmitri during this period. For 10 points, name this period of civil disorder in Russia that ended with the establishment of the Romanov Dynasty.",
      "answer": "the Time of Troubles"
    },
    {
      "question": "This island was the location of the extremely successful Carlson’s Patrol. Had Gunichi Mikawa not retreated prematurely, he could have destroyed American transports at this island after the Battle of Savo Island. American forces invaded this island due to the construction of an airfield on its Lunga Point; after its capture, that airfield was renamed Henderson Field. For 10 points, name this island in the Solomons, the site of the first Allied counter-offensive after the Battle of Midway in 1942.",
      "answer": "Guadalcanal"
    },
    {
      "question": "The breakup of Pannotia at the beginning of this period led to the formation of the supercontinent Gondwana. After discovering many lagerstatten from this period in a certain country, Adam Sedgwick named it after the Latin name for Wales. This period was followed by the Ordovician, and it saw the first appearance of trilobites. It began approximately 540 million years ago. For 10 points, name this first period of the Paleozoic [pale-ee-oh-ZOH-ic] Era, which contained a namesake “explosion” of biodiversity.",
      "answer": "Cambrian period"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization recently discussed the Doha Development Agenda in the context of improving the position of developing countries. This organization conducts periodic international economic talks known as “rounds.” The 1995 Marrakech Agreement created this organization to displace the GATT. In 1999, a conference hosted by this organization in Seattle was the subject of massive street protests. For 10 points, name this international organization that regulates the exchange of goods and services among nations.",
      "answer": "World Trade Organization"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man had previously been an Orthodox Party candidate before he was arrested. This man was the leader of a group that used the Granma yacht. He gave the “History will absolve me” speech following his arrest after the failure of the assault of the 26th of July Movement on the Moncada barracks. After his return, he led guerrilla fighters in the Sierra Maestra. For 10 points, identify this man who overthrew Fulgencio [ful-HEN-see-oh] Batista to become leader of Cuba.",
      "answer": "Fidel Alejandro Castro Ruz"
    },
    {
      "question": "A book by this thinker includes the chapter \"Formal Sex Relations\" as well as a close analysis of the kava ceremony. In one book, this thinker described the taupou system, which required women to keep their virginity. Derek Freeman attacked the work of this student of Franz Boas in a book titled for her \"Fateful Hoaxing.\" Much of her research was conducted on the island of Ta'u in the Pacific Ocean. For 10 points, name this anthropologist who wrote Coming of Age in Samoa.",
      "answer": "Margaret Mead"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bernard of Saxe-Weimar led cavalry into French service during this war that included the Battle of Allerheim. The city of Magdeburg was sacked by General Tilly during this war, whose early “Danish” phase resulted from the disastrous folly of pro-Protestant King Christian IV. For 10 points, name this religious war in Germany that lasted from 1618 to 1648?",
        "answer": "Thirty Years' War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Thirty Years' War was ended by what peace accord signed at Munster and Osnabruck that is considered the foundation of the modern system of state sovereignty?",
        "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Coronation glyphs from this culture are found on Altar Q at the site of Copan. Religious traditions among these people based on the k’atun cycle are recorded in folding books called chilam balaam. This culture’s most notable creation includes a “Long Count” system and is more accurate than a Gregorian counterpart. For 10 points, what Mesoamerican culture created a calendar that predicted the world’s doom in 2012?",
        "answer": "Maya"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which great ruler of Palenque had the longest-known reign in Western hemisphere history?",
        "answer": "Pacal the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This sect has an understanding which allows member congregations to use the word “Greater” in naming themselves. In 1995, it formally apologized for its role in perpetuating slavery and racism. This sect began with a convention in Augusta. For 10 points, name this largest protestant denomination in the United States, named for its geographic origins.",
        "answer": "Southern Baptist Convention"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Southern Baptist pastor and televangelist founded Liberty University in Lynchburg, Virginia.",
        "answer": "Jerry Lamon Falwell, Sr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man had the word “Freude” replaced with “Freiheit” while conducting a performance of Beethoven’s Ninth at the Brandenburg Gate in 1989. John F. Kennedy was the dedicatee of his Kaddish symphony. He collaborated with Jerome Robbins and Stephen Sondheim on a musical about warring Puerto Rican and Caucasian gangs based on Romeo and Juliet. For 10 points, name this Jewish composer of West Side Story.",
        "answer": "Leonard Bernstein"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bernstein composed the soundtrack for this Elia Kazan movie about a corrupt longshoremen’s union, in which Marlon Brando’s character laments “I coulda been a contender!”",
        "answer": "On the Waterfront"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A \"monkey-eating\" type of this animal is native to the Philippines. Deforestation in South America threatens the habitat of a large \"harpy\" type of this bird. The Holy Roman Empire used a double-headed one to represent the church and the state. A blue depiction of this kind of animal was used as the emblem of the National Recovery Administration. For 10 points, name this bird, whose \"bald\" type is an American national symbol.",
        "answer": "eagles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A black double-eagle is shown on the flag of what country, which became the first officially atheist country in the world under the rule of Enver Hoxha [“ho-jah”]?",
        "answer": "Republic of Albania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "As governor, this man authorized the invasion of Illinois by George Rogers Clark. As a lawyer, he defended his home colony’s Two Penny Act in the so-called “Parson’s Cause.” This man succeeded Lord Dunmore to become the first non-royal governor of Virginia, and said in one speech “If this be treason, make the most of it.” For 10 points, name this man who declared “give me liberty or give me death!”",
        "answer": "Patrick Henry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry served as a member of this legislature of colonial Virginia, the first such body in North America.",
        "answer": "House of Burgesses"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man succeeded William Marcy as Governor of New York, and this man was friends with political boss Thurlow Weed. This anti-slavery politician, who was wounded by Lewis Powell, tried to purchase the U.S. Virgin Islands before buying land from Russia. For 10 points name this Secretary of State under Lincoln and Johnson who bought Alaska, his namesake “folly.”",
        "answer": "William Henry Seward"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Seward lost the 1860 Republican nomination for President, as did this man who would serve as Treasury Secretary under Lincoln.",
        "answer": "Salmon Portland Chase"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ivy Mike made use of this process, which is enabled by the Teller-Ulam design. Inertial confinement attempts to cause this reaction in a deuterium or tritium pellet. A Japanese fishing boat’s crew were affected by the Castle Bravo test of a weapon relying on this process. For 10 points, identify this joining together of atomic nuclei, used to power a hydrogen bomb.",
        "answer": "nuclear fusion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What massive Russian fusion bomb’s 1961 test detonation created the largest human- caused explosion in history?",
        "answer": "Tsar Bomba"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "JAMESTOWN",
      "prompt": "During the colonization of Jamestown, who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The man who led the colony through its most difficult times and mapped the Chesapeake Bay in the Discovery?",
          "answer": "John Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Indian princess who converted to Christianity and moved to England before dying of smallpox?",
          "answer": "Pocahontas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Both the term for the Indian Confederacy neighboring Jamestown, and its leader?",
          "answer": "Powhatan"
        },
        {
          "question": "The name of the company which funded Jamestown in hopes of finding gold?",
          "answer": "Virginia Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "The man who began the cultivation of tobacco in Jamestown?",
          "answer": "John Rolfe"
        },
        {
          "question": "The period of time where the colony nearly failed due to lack of supplies?",
          "answer": "Starving Times"
        },
        {
          "question": "The largest of the three ships originally sent to colonize Jamestown?",
          "answer": "Susan Constant"
        },
        {
          "question": "The governor who saved the colony with extra supplies and led the first war against the Indians?",
          "answer": "Third and Twelfth Baron De La Warr"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AGE OF EXPLORATION",
      "prompt": "Which European explorer…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Discovered the New World in 1492?",
          "answer": "Christopher Columbus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the initial leader of the first ships to circumnavigate the globe but died in the Philippines?",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Magellan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Named Florida while unsuccessfully searching for the Fountain of Youth?",
          "answer": "Juan Ponce de Leon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first to reach India by sea in 1498 by rounding the Cape of Good Hope?",
          "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Reached the Cape of Good Hope but his crew would not let him round it?",
          "answer": "Bartolomeu Dias"
        },
        {
          "question": "In the pay of France explored the North American coast? The entrance to New York harbor was named for him.",
          "answer": "Giovanni da Verrazzano"
        },
        {
          "question": "Launched the age of discovery by funding and supporting Portuguese exploration of the African coast?",
          "answer": "Prince Henry the Navigator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sailed to Canada for England in 1497?",
          "answer": "John Cabot"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "SPANISH-AMERICAN WAR",
      "prompt": "During the Spanish-American War who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The American President who launched the war?",
          "answer": "William McKinley"
        },
        {
          "question": "The European capital where the treaty ending the war was signed?",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "The naval battle in the Philippines where George Dewey defeated the Spanish fleet?",
          "answer": "Battle of Manila Bay"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Filipino independence leader who fought the US after the war?",
          "answer": "Emilio Famy Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "The rival of Joseph Pulitzer whose New York Journal rallied support for the war?",
          "answer": "William Randolph Hearst"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Assistant Secretary of the Navy at the start of the war, who was one of the Rough Riders?",
          "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "The 1898 battle in Cuba where the Rough Riders made their famous charge on Kettle Hill?",
          "answer": "San Juan Hill"
        },
        {
          "question": "The nickname given to the African-American cavalry regiments that saw the hardest action at San Juan Hill?",
          "answer": "Buffalo Soldiers"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 1960s, several of this country’s Christian political parties merged to form the Christian Democratic Appeal. At the end of World War II, it suffered the “Hunger Winter.” Filmmaker Theo (20 pts)",
        "van Gogh was killed in this country, where Queen Beatrix abdicated in 2013. This country’s former colonies include Suriname and (10 pts)",
        "Indonesia, and the United Nations’ International Court of Justice is based in its city The Hague. For 10 points, name this country where Anne Frank hid in Amsterdam."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of the Netherlands"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Brahmagupta sometimes lends his name to this mathematician’s identity writing a product of sums of squares itself as a sum of squares. This man’s most famous book was among the first to use Arabic numerals. (20 pts)",
        "Binet’s [bih-nays] formula gives values of a sequence named after this man, and the ratio between those values approximates the (10 pts)",
        "golden ratio. This mathematician developed his most famous result by considering the monthly reproduction of rabbits. For 10 points, identify this mathematician whose book Liber Abaci introduced a sequence beginning 1,1,2,3,5."
      ],
      "answer": "Leonardo Fibonacci"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man received a warning from the Boston police for including a dominant seventh in an arrangement of “The Star-Spangled Banner”. W.H. Auden wrote a four-haiku text for this man’s composition Elegy for (20 pts)",
        "J.F.K., and he collaborated again with Auden on the William Hogarth-inspired opera The Rake’s Progress. One of his most famous works opens with a high (10 pts)",
        "bassoon solo and was accompanied by Sergei Diaghilev’s [dee-AH-gi-levs] choreography for Vaslav Nijinsky [nih-JIN-ski]. For 10 points, name this composer who was present during the riot sparked by the 1913 premiere of his ballet The Rite of Spring."
      ],
      "answer": "Igor Stravinsky"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Restitution for a Canadian equivalent of this policy was passed by the government of Brian Mulroney. Ansel Adams photographed people affected by this policy at (20 pts)",
        "Manzanar. Places like Tule Lake were created by this policy’s early advocates on the State Personnel Board of (10 pts)",
        "California. Much of this policy was established through Executive Order 9066. Ex parte Endo concerned a man detained as part of this policy. For 10 points, name this policy that confined Americans of a certain Asian ethnicity during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Japanese-American Internment during World War II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A document opposing this policy begins, “The People Shall Govern!”. That Freedom Charter was drawn up in a 1955 Congress of the People by Z.K. Matthews and (20 pts)",
        "Lionel Bernstein, among other activists against this policy, which led its country to recognize the TBVC states. This policy officially began with the 1948 election of the Reunited (10 pts)",
        "National Party under D. F. Malan. This policy’s Terrorism Act led to Steve Biko’s [bee-kohs] death in police custody, and it was opposed by Nelson Mandela. For 10 points, name this policy of South African racial segregation."
      ],
      "answer": "apartheid"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of the signatories of this treaty would later be stationed in Constantinople. One side argued that its terms mandated the renunciation of claims to the Bay Islands and the (20 pts)",
        "Mosquito Coast. Many observers thought this treaty named for Lord Palmerston's minister to Washington and Zachary Taylor's Secretary of State violated the (10 pts)",
        "Monroe Doctrine. Eventually abrogated by the 1901 Hay-Pauncefote Treaty, for 10 points, identify this 1850 treaty declaring that neither the US nor Britain would build a canal in Central America without mutual consent."
      ],
      "answer": "Clayton-Bulwer Treaty"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One monarch with this name was betrayed by nobles under William Kirkcaldy after an agreement at Carberry Hill. That monarch of this name was accused of conspiring with the Earl of Bothwell to order the murder of Lord (20 pts)",
        "Darnley and of writing the Casket Letters. Another monarch with this name suppressed Wyatt’s Rebellion after the announcement of (10 pts)",
        "her marriage to Philip of Spain and oversaw the execution of Thomas Cranmer. For 10 points, give the name shared by James I’s mother and a Queen whose persecution of Protestants gave rise to her nickname “Bloody”."
      ],
      "answer": "Mary"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This colony's soldiers carried out the Pavonia massacre against a tribe which it would fight in the Peach Tree War. The (20 pts)",
        "Eight Men council was created by a leader of this colony who was petitioned in the Flushing Remonstrance. This colony granted land to patroons and fought Kieft's War against the Lenape [leh-nah-pay] tribe. This colony (10 pts)",
        "cheaply purchased an island under director Peter Minuit. For 10 points, name this colony once led by the peg-legged Peter Stuyvesant, which had a capital at New Amsterdam and was replaced by New York."
      ],
      "answer": "New Netherlands"
    }
  ]
}